Welcome back to AM Northwest. You
know if you love to shop estate sales,
hidden gems are everywhere.
If you know what to look for, here to
share his expert tips on estate silver,
we welcome back
antique appraiser Gary Germer. Always
good to see you Gary. You too Helen.
Okay I'm a huge fan of silver. I've
got like my great-grandmother's
silver and I love it and I use it. And where
did you get all of this? Well most all of this
came
from a hoarder's house in Central Oregon. Wow.
The family contacted me after they spent a year
clearing out the trash and dad had bought all
this back in the 70s and stuffed it away in the
back of
closets and they said is this worth anything
and I said they are. We started here with these
this
spoon collection. These are what they call Apostle
spoons and these were made when Queen Elizabeth
the first was on the throne. Wow. So they date to
these are 400 years old and as the name implies
each of these guys on here
are different apostles.
And you tell which one you got by what he's
holding. Peter has a key to the kingdom and things
like that.
So how much are these guys worth? Well
these are worth about $3,000 a piece.
Whoa. In today's market.
They were a lot then. People back then in the
1500s we think of silver and how these elaborate
place settings were back in the 1500s early
1600s you have to understand that most people had
a
wooden spoon that they carved out and ate with.
As a matter of fact spoon comes from more means
a piece of
wood is what it means. And so. Oh.
This would have been a time when you did you had
a spoon and that's what you had and you carried
it with you and
oftentimes among the wealthy they would give
these as christening presents to new babies.
Wow.
And then as time went on that you know the time
change and they had the same spoon but you'll
see these are what they
call a seal top spoon and it's just this baluster
and then see and they bounce really well too.
They still have their
bounce.
And then on further.
These are Puritan spoons the Puritans were
fighting against the idea of idolatry.
Oh I see.
So there's a whole segment on why it became
plainer and plainer but these are all you'll never
see these outside usually
outside of a museum.
Amazing and then these.
This stuff here is a little bit later this
would have been the late 16 early into the 1700s
this would have been on George
Washington's breakfast table.
Incredible.
These.
Is this a creamer?
Yeah.
As things change they stay the same.
It was as funny.
In the 1750s to pour cream out
of a cow's mouth as it is now.
As it is now yeah.
You know the classics never die.
These are interesting these were done by a lady
named Hester Bateman and she was a silversmith
in the 1700s.
Was that unusual to have
a woman as a silversmith?
Unheard of and she was extremely successful at
it she and her sons they did we think they did
the work and she was the business behind it
and they were fighting against this new idea of
silver plate so they did what they called
sheet silver and so it's a little bit thinner.
Oh I see.
But they did these neoclassical designs and
just remarkable workmanship but yet it was done
at a price where the middle class could afford
it and they were in tremendous demand and it
went three generations and the business
finally faltered in the mid 1800s.
What was this used for?
Toast?
Yeah that's a toast rack.
Oh you put your toast.
You're probably just putting
yours on a plate aren't you?
You know if you were.
Oh wow.
Yeah this is a toast rack Hester
Bateman and this is a wine funnel.
Wow.
So you would decant a bottle of wine.
Right.
And you would.
And you would put it through here to filter out
any sediment that might have been in the bottom
of the bottle.
Okay and these little guys.
Aren't they fun little dishes?
Yeah.
Is it just like to put little candies?
Yeah these would have been just
little candies or little side dishes.
You wouldn't have used it for salt like a mad
because silver will corrode that and usually salt
dishes will have a glass liner in it.
Okay.
But it would have been more for
like a candy or just a little side.
And what do you look for when you look at
silver and you see something at estate sales?
What do you look for?
Well you want to see if it's sterling.
Okay.
And if it's American silver.
To find these things is like you
know finding a unicorn almost.
Right.
You know.
But English silver is clearly
marked with hallmarks.
It will have a walking lion passant.
American silver should
say sterling or 925.
It will let you know.
And so this is more what
you'll end up finding.
This is more Victorian.
We can see how the styles change.
My point was this is
1700s into the late 1800s.
You have pieces here.
Made by Tiffany.
More ornate.
That are more beautifully in hand.
And this was made in India
for the British style.
So you have cobra handles.
And then the sets.
So you go back in the 1500s.
You might have a spoon.
Now we have a fork and a spoon.
We have one here for horseradish.
This is for baked potato.
This is for macaroni.
I mean you know you can't
just serve it with anything.
And then how do you care?
I have as I said silver.
How do you care for silver?
You should first of all use it.
Yeah I agree.
And you don't put it in the dishwasher.
You don't.
You don't clean it.
You shouldn't.
And then you shouldn't put it in.
Clean it with a dip.
The dip watery stuff.
You use a cream paste.
The cream paste.
Okay that's what I use.
But the first thing if
you go to an estate sale.
And you got a really tarnished piece.
The first thing you want to do is wash it.
Carefully to get any food or dirt.
Don't use anything abrasive.
And you'll get a lot of
the tarnish off that way.
Right.
And then from then on you want
to use a soft cloth and a paste.
Okay and one last thing.
This little bird napkin
ring is the cutest.
So what time period is this again?
This would have been done
right around 1900, 1890, 1910.
Everybody had their napkin ring.
And they had figural napkin
rings if you were really special.
Yes.
Got your kids to sit down at
the table and get their napkin.
That is fantastic.
And lastly well let's do
this while we have it here.
This is something if you're an estate.
Sale person.
These are serving spoons.
Now the spoons themselves
were made in the early 1800s.
Around 1805.
And you can tell this
on the back of these.
There's the British hallmark.
And the hallmark has a date
on it that can tell you.
But they were plain.
And then in the end of the century
they ended up doing these bowls.
So you take your spoons
back in and gussy them up.
I love it.
Because it would be more ornate then.
Gary this was a lot of fun.
Thank you so much.
Thanks for having me.
Okay we'll put all the information
on our website at KAT.com.